Rhiannon: We often hear Mental Health
problems discussed regarding adults,
but over the last five years, surveys of
the mental health of children and young
people in England found that over 15
percent had at least one mental disorder
when assessed, and over 5 percent met
the criteria for 2 or more according to
the NHS, and these number are increasing.
Leah: Approximately 50 percent of lifelong
mental health problems, have started by
the time a young person reaches their
mid-teens, and around 75 percent by
their mid-20s, although most treatment
typically starts a few years later.
Rhiannon: When looking at data on the
mental health of very young children, aged
2 to 4, this is something still rather new
and experimental, but some results suggest
that approximately 5 percent of pre-school
children may have a mental disorder,
with a higher rate in boys than in girls.
Leah: Over half of children and
young people with a probable mental
disorder report having sleep problems.
In teenage girls two thirds
with a probable mental disorder,
had seen or heard an argument
among adults in their household.
Rhiannon: Over half the children at school
age with a probable mental disorder,
have regular support from their school.
And school age children with a
probable mental disorder are more
than twice as likely to live in a
household with financial difficulties.
Leah: Children who suffer from
neglect are more likely to experience
mental health problems including
depression, post-traumatic stress
disorder and attention deficit
and hyperactivity disorder.
This may impact their relationships
in later life, including
with their own children.
Rhiannon: Family mental health
problems, a hostile environment and
breakup, are proven to negatively
affect a child’s mental wellbeing.
Mental health problems in children and
young people can include depression,
anxiety and conduct disorder, and
are often a direct response to
what is happening in their lives.
Leah: The emotional wellbeing
of children is just as important
as their physical health.
Good mental health allows children and
young people to develop the resilience to
cope with whatever life throws at them and
grow into well-rounded, healthy adults.
Rhiannon: Social media, also now gives
access to information for young people
to find out more about what help is
available, but it can also open doors
to getting bad advice or misinformation.
Leah: 30 years ago, information on mental
health was more restricted to health
professionals, scholarly articles or
books, whereas today there are websites
covering all aspects and issues.
This can have a positive effect in
informing children and young people that
there is help out there, if they want it.
Rhiannon: But, mismanaged or taken out of
context can also be negative by opening
them to a world of pitfalls which can have
further impact on their mental health.
Leah: It’s important then, to use
this knowledge and these resources
to help, while not allowing some of
these same avenues to undermine the
work we are trying to accomplish.